This is the biggest, most in-depth video about bowling ever.
How bowling balls are made,
the best way to throw them,
maximize strikes,
how the lanes are oiled,
what it takes to be a pro
and how this sport has continually been reinvented
for literally thousands of years, up to the present day.
This is the science of bowling,
the most popular participatory sport in the United States.
I'm super impressed with how that went.
- I'm even more impressed than you are.
- What is inside a bowling ball?
I sent this ball to Creative Electron to get a 3D x-ray scan
and this is the result.
What is that?
I always expected bowling balls to be, y’know, perfect solid spheres,
but there's something inside here and it's not symmetric
and it's not even centered in the ball.
So I went to Storm Bowling,
one of only 11 bowling ball manufacturers in the world
to find out how bowling balls are made.
- Yeah. Basically when we make bowling balls,
we always start in the center
and the center part of the bowling ball is the weight block.
And as you can see this is an example of an asymmetrical shaped weight block,
so it's actually a different shape about the X, the Y and the Z axis.
- The weight blocks are embedded in a core of lightweight glass beads.
- That is so silky-soft.
I feel like I have not felt anything this soft.
What's the difference in density between this sort of filling material and this core?
- It's quite a bit.
About two and a half to three times more dense
in the inner weight block than it is in the core material.
- If you were to look for example at this actual core,
number one, it says 960
which means that it weighs 9.60 pounds.
And then the description here underneath, which is a 03,
this indicates what type of a weight block is inside of it.
- What happens over here?
- So this area right here is our urethane area.
So basically what we have are a number of different tanks that are set up.
So there's a chemical reaction that occurs
once it actually fills the mold
and we pour that cover stock material around the pour.
It gets extremely hot in just a matter of minutes.
You go right down here,
she's actually pouring the pin material inside the tops of those cores.
So you can see for this particular bowling ball,
it's a bright orange type of a material,
and she's actually filling that hole with that plug material.
We've got the lane at the right here
which is where we take the balls that come out of the mold.
And then they actually spin almost 2000 RPM.
On top of there there's the blades that come around
and it actually makes the balls perfectly round.
So they'll actually trim those up.
- [Derek] Since the balls are not symmetric,
they are heavier on one side than the other.
- And you can see there the last four or five pumps of air,
where it actually floats the air then it stops and pauses,
that the ball has completely settled.
And then basically a needle will come out from the bottom part
and all of a sudden it'll shoot it up.
And then it'll be where the center of gravity is on the surface of the ball.
- When it comes right off the lane, right here,
it is extremely porous and very, very dull,
and there is a ton of friction
between the ball and the lane at this point.
So every ball from right here will be smoothed up,
it's just a matter of how much it's gonna be smoothed up
in order to get what is the desired finish.
- [Derek] But before they can use these balls,
they have to be drilled.
But that is specific to each bowler.
How many balls are you making a day?
- [Steve] We're making over 3000 balls in a day now.
they come out of this plant right here.
- Wild.
I found the bowling ball equivalent of clickbait.
"You won't believe your eyes",
"The mind bending hook".
- Right?
- Yeah. It's how you have to sell your stuff.
I get it.
- Exactly. Yeah.
- [Derek] But how did it come to be this way?
Well, bowling seems to be an ancient game.
Archeologists have found wall drawings of a sport
that looks like bowling in an ancient Egyptian tomb dating back 7,000 years.
In Germany, bowling was used as a religious ritual.
Pins represented your sins,
so you're a good Christian if you could knock them all down.
Martin Luther himself was apparently a bowling fanatic
and fixed the number of pins at nine.
When the game made its way over to America,
nine-pin bowling was banned because it promoted gambling.
The legend goes that people cleverly came up with
10-pin bowling to get around the law.
Whoa, totally different game.
Today in the US, nine-pin bowling is only played in Texas
because it was the one state that didn't ban it,
instead, charging it tax.
Bowling lanes are about three-and-a-half-feet wide
and 60 feet long down to the headpin.
I'm using Imperial units here because that's actually how they're defined.
The lane is made of 39 narrow boards
that bowlers number for reference.
They used to be made of maple and pinewood,
but these days, most lanes are synthetic
and made of fine particles coated with melamine resin.
One game of bowling gives you 10 frames
with two throws per frame
to try to knock down all 10 pins.
The highest score you can get in a game without a strike is only 190,
but strikes allow you to double count your next two throws,
so a perfect game with all strikes gives you a score of 300.
If you're anything like me,
the whole game is just trying to throw the ball as straight as you can
down the middle of the lane, hit the headpin
and try to take as many other pins down with it as possible.
Do you wanna give me any tips or-
- I've watched LeBron bowling, you won't be worse than him.
- You say that now you.
- See, that's what I would normally do.
And I would normally be like
reasonably happy with a shot like that.
But for pro-bowlers like Pete Weber or Chris Barnes,
- [Narrator] For a perfect game,
- Yes!
- [Derek] The game is different.
And not just because they are way better than me.
- [Narrator] And he get it!
- Who you think that you are? I am.
Hitting the headpins square on is not the perfect strategy.
If you hit the headpin square on going straight,
you're unlikely to knock down all the pins.
You could end up with a split where the ball goes through the middle,
or with the ball deflecting off to one side after hitting the headpin.
Chances for a strike are much higher
if the center of the ball hits the pins just to one side of the headpin.
Board 17 and a half.
In which case the ball takes out the 1, 3, 5, and 9 pins,
which take out the others.
- So we want the ball to hit the 1 pin, the 3,
the pin behind the 1, which is the 5 pin.
And then the 9 or the 8 and the 9.
- [Derek] You want the ball to hit all of those pins?
- [Chris] Yeah.
- Now the pins don't always fall this way,
but the pin shape helps.
Pins roll in circles like eggs,
which help knock down the others.
- That's right baby!
Come on, don't miss.
You wanted it, you got it.
- [Derek] But to have an over 90% chance
of getting a strike,
the center of the ball has to hit
with an error smaller than half a board.
Needless to say, throwing a ball 60 feet
straight at a target smaller than a dime is a tough task.
Especially to do it consistently.
Luckily there is a better way.
- Now, if we look at the pins
and as you look at them from here, from straight on,
the spot between the headpin,
the one that's in the center,
and the 3 pin which is just right at that,
that gap's pretty narrow.
But as the ball hooks more,
now we basically shift over,
and now that space is considerably wider.
- [Derek] If you can hit the pins not head-on,
but at an angle of six degrees,
you dramatically increase your chances of knocking them all down.
Now the margin for error is greater.
The ball can be coming in anywhere from board 17 to 18 and a half,
that is a board and a half of room.
And that still gives you
greater than a 90% chance of a strike.
Now, six degrees may not sound like a lot,
but it's actually extremely difficult to hit.
The problem is, if you wanted to throw the ball
straight at the pins and hit them at six degrees,
you would have to be bowling from 3/4 over on the next lane.
And that is impossible.
Well, with the two gutters in between and all.
So the solution is you've got to curve the ball on one lane.
I feel like I have never spun a ball.
Is that… (laughs) Is that hard?
- So if you've got it under your hand and the ball's underneath,
and you're trying to spin it,
that's especially the motion that players use these days.
- [Derek] This really became a big part of the sport by accident.
- The wood gets beat up with the damage from all the balls going into it.
And so they basically created slip agents,
lubricants much like oil on a car
so that the lanes didn't get damaged so quickly.
- [Derek] So the original idea was to protect the wood.
- The original idea was just to protect the surface of the lane.
It was not to manufacture anything
for my competitive-scoring type environment.
- But applying oil to protect the wood
meant that balls no longer grip the lane
and roll without slipping down to the pins.
Instead they could skid,
rotating not in their direction of travel.
Now, I've been to a lot of bowling alleys before making this video
and I noticed it was a bit greasy,
but I always thought that was just the nature of bowling alleys.
Like the stinky rental shoes.
I didn't know they intentionally put oil on the lanes.
Vox has a great video specifically about oil patterns.
These days, there are machines specifically for applying oil to the lanes.
- [Chris] And then as proprietors went,
"Huh, well yeah, it does make the ball skid.
Well, if I put more in the middle than the outside
my baller's bowl a little bit better and they're happier."
And then as technology advances like everything does
now we have $30,000 lane machines
that can put a specific amount of oil on each board.
- [Derek] They work kind of like dot matrix printers.
They can lay the oil on
with varying degrees of thickness across the lane
and extend the oil pattern different distances.
There are hundreds of different patterns that can be used.
Usually the oil extends about 2/3 the way down the lane,
so to around 40 or 45 feet.
But there's always a dry patch of wood before the pins
that increases the friction with the ball,
getting it to start rolling without slipping.
And this leads to the three parts of any pro bowler's throw.
The skid, the hook and the roll.
When a bowler releases the ball,
it can be going 20 miles an hour
and spinning at 500 RPM.
That's nearly 10 full revolutions per second.
Right-handers typically throw the ball to the right
on the lane while spinning it to the left.
During the skid phase, the ball slides down the lane
spinning but not rolling.
As it comes to the end of the oil,
the friction increases and the ball accelerates to the left.
It hooks because of its spin,
and the spin starts lining up with the direction of travel,
leading to stage three, roll.
The ball is rolling without slipping as it barrels into the pins.
Ideally, as close to that six degree angle as possible.
Like the ball starts on the left side of the lane,
goes straight across almost rightmost.
Then hooks like at the last minute, rolls in there.
So that's almost like a perfect shot, right?
straight in the pocket there.
- Close.
- Yeah. That's where you want to hit the pins. Yeah.
- My very first game,
it was ABC back then, American Bowling Congress.
I filled out the application to bowl in men's league.
Dad gave them the letter saying that I could,
and the first game of bowl was 300
and they handed me a hundred dollars too,
and it was like, yeah, making money now.
And actually, my first, my sixth, my ninth,
my 13th, 17th, 20th were all 300 games.
I like, seven or eight 300 in my first year of men's league.
- [Derek] How do you explain that?
- To shoot 300 you have to get lucky somewhere along the line.
- [Derek] Like that.
- Like that.
It came in to hit the 1, 3, 5, 9.
And that that's what we call the perfect shot.
- I mean, you just keep hitting them.
That's almost the identical shot.
Look at that, that yellow and the purple,
they're almost exactly on top of each other.
- Oh, it just goes a little bit straight.
- That one, the purple one
was just a little bit higher on the head pin,
but it still hit the 1, 3 and the 5 and the 9.
Can't get much better.
- [Derek] This type of throw is only possible because of the oil.
If you try to throw a ball the same way on an unoiled lane.
Oh no.
It just doesn't work.
Can I actually ask you to bowl like you normally would,
but on the dry lane?
I know it's crazy.
I just want to see what like a normal shot
would look like if there was no oil.
- No oil.
It's gonna hit the lane and go in the left gutter.
- That's what I want to see.
- All right.
You're gonna throw it just like it's a regular lane.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- Oh yeah, there's no oil on the lane so the ball can't get down.
As soon as it hits the lane, it's going to start hooking,
y'know, 'cause if you do this, who's skidding a ball on this.
- So they want the oil.
- Yeah. We need the oil.
If we didn't have oil, this is what it would be.
And nobody would have fun.
This is not fun. - The bowling sucks,
We don't want to do this.
- For pro bowlers, the oil on the lane is a key part of the game.
- Oh whoa.
- Wow. Hey.
- Do you look at the oil?
Are you trying to scope it out
or are you just kind of guessing?
- I usually don't look at the oil. I let my ball be the guide.
Y‘know, I know some guys that are… they get down like this
and they look in and it's like…
they're seeing the same thing I do when I sit down, I go like that.
Nothing. I see absolutely nothing.
- Whether you can see it or not,
figuring out the condition of oil on the lane
can make the difference between a strike and a miss.
As the game wears on the bowling balls move the oil around,
pushing it further down the lane and stripping it off the most common paths.
So players have to adjust to the changing conditions.
Some people say left-handers have an advantage
because right-handers aren't playing
on their side of the lane.
At most bowling alleys,
they use a pattern of oil that is thicker in the middle
and thinner out toward the edges.
This is a forgiving layout
because balls that drift too far out start to hook earlier,
while balls going straighter can continue down the lane for longer
before making their turn into the pins.
But for pro bowlers, the oil conditions vary
and players have to adjust their games to the conditions.
Some people seem to think that like
league bowlers are better than they are, maybe,
'cause they say like, "Oh, this league bowler
can shoot two 10, and I just saw pro shoot two 10."
- That's why they call it league
because you bowl on the same shot every week.
Because each week on tour,
I'm bowling on a different condition.
Not the same condition every week.
We have Cheetah, Chameleon, Scorpion, shark,
one more. - Bear?
- Bear. Yeah.
- [Derek] But it's not just the oil on the lanes
但是改变保龄球运动的
that is transformed bowling.
不仅仅是球道上的油
It's also the balls themselves.
还有球本身
- Hard rubber bowling balls was what I started with.
我从硬质橡胶球开始打
Maybe mid 70's and then the Yellow Dot,
大约70年代中期换成了“哥伦比亚黄点”  这是种塑料球
the Columbia Yellow Dot, which is a plastic ball.
And then they came out with urethane bowling balls.
然后聚氨酯球出现了
I won a lot of titles with the urethane stuff.
我用这种球拿到了不少冠军
And then they come out with the reactive resin bowling balls.
再之后出现的是活性树脂材质的球
- [Derek] Reactive resin is just a modified polyurethane
这就是一种改良的聚氨酯
with a more porous surface, which gives it more grip in the oil.
它的表面疏松多孔  在涂油的地面上抓地性更好
It's the most popular surface or cover stock for bowling balls today.
这是当下最流行的保龄球表面涂层
Balls started out as perfect symmetrically-weighted spheres.
保龄球最初是重量完美对称分布的球体
And when you go to a bowling alley, the house balls there are still just that.
如果你去保龄球馆看看  那里的公用球仍然是这样
But when you drill holes in the ball,
但是如果你在球上钻孔
you take some weight out of one side.
就会让球在某个方向上的重量减少
So to rebalance it, ball manufacturers
保龄球的制造商为了重新调整球的重量
added a small pancake weight on the same side as the holes.
会在打孔的方向上加个配重饼
But then ball manufacturers got the idea,
但是制造商想到了
they could add different weights inside the ball to improve their performance.
他们可以在球的内部放置不同的配重  来提升球的性能
You can have two balls that look identical from the outside,
外观相同、重量相等的两颗保龄球
weigh exactly the same amount,
and yet roll differently.
转起来可以完全不同
If the mass is more concentrated around the axis of rotation,
如果质量在旋转轴周围更加集中
say you have a dense cylinder inside the ball.
比如在球内嵌了一个致密的圆柱体
Well then it has a lower moment of inertia.
这颗球的转动惯量会较小
And this means for the same amount of energy input,
这意味着  对于相同大小的能量输入
it will spin faster.
它会旋转得更快
In bowling, they prefer to talk about an analogous concept.
在保龄球术语中有个相似的概念
Radius of gyration or RG.
回转半径 缩写为RG
If you were to concentrate the entire mass of the ball
如果把整个球的质量集中在
onto a hoop with the same moment of inertia,
一个有相同转动惯量的圆环上
it's radius would be the radius of gyration.
这个圆环的半径就是回转半径
So smaller radius of gyration just means lower moment of inertia,
所以回转半径小就意味着转动惯量小
which translates into more rotation that a bowler can get on the ball.
也就能使保龄球手将球转得更快
- Some people are lower leverage
it just spins faster, like,
eh, it's of crazy, and then
somebody finally did a study on that.
Yeah, it turns out,
yeah, it's like 8% for every 0.05.
And so it depends on what your leverage is.
Can be fairly significant.
- [Derek] An ability to spin the balls faster,
只要能让球转的更快
gives a bowler the ability to hook the ball more sharply further down the lane,
保龄球手就越可能在球道更远处  让球拐得更大
giving them a better chance of achieving that six degree entry angle.
也就越可能达到6°的入射角
What was amazing for me to learn is that
配重块的知识使我大受震撼
the weight blocks in these balls aren't even centered.
球里面的配重块甚至不位于中心
There's a heavy side and a lighter side on purpose,
制作商有意将它们制成一侧重一侧轻
and you can find and mark this side
让球在气垫上自由旋转  就可以找到哪边重
by letting the ball spin freely on a cushion of air,
until it comes to rest, heavy side down.
直到它静止下来 此时重的一侧向下
They showed me a great demonstration
他们向我绝妙地展示了
of how the position of the center of gravity
重心的位置对球的运动能产生怎样的影响
can affect the movement of the ball.
When the center of mass is on the left side of the ball,
当质心位于球的左侧时
it pulls in the same direction as the spin,
它的拉力和旋转摩擦力同向
helping the ball hook to the left, into the pins,
帮助球往左侧拐弯 击倒球瓶
- Same exact ball, same numbers,
同一个球 同一个码数
just different static and balance basically.
基本上只有平衡位置不同
- [Derek] But here is a flipped bowling ball
而这是个镜像翻转的保龄球
where the center of mass is on the right.
,它的质心位于右侧
Now the ball starts to hook into the left,
现在球开始钩向左侧
but at the end, something weird happens.
但是最后奇怪的事情发生了
The center of mass pulls it over to the right.
质心把球拉向右侧
This effect is only really noticeable when the ball is thrown slowly.
这个效应只在缓慢投球的时候比较明显
These days, there are tons of different weight blocks that go inside bowling balls
现在的保龄球里  有各种各样的配重块
and they can be grouped into two categories, symmetric and asymmetric.
它们可以分为两类：对称的块和不对称的块
For all these weight blocks,
不管是哪类配重块
the minimum moment of inertia or in bowling terms, the smallest RG axis
转动惯量最小的轴  或者用保龄球术语来说“RG最小”的轴
is identified by a pin, which is visible on the outside of the ball.
都会在球的表面有所标记
It will spin most easily about this axis.
保龄球绕此轴旋转最不费力
For the symmetric weight blocks,
对于对称的配重块
the ball doesn't change as you rotate it about this axis.
球绕对称轴转动时  质量分布不变
So the maximum moment of inertia
所以要获得最大转动惯量
is rotating about any axis that passes through the equator of the ball.
只需让转动轴穿过赤道（即转动轴垂直于左图的对称轴）即可
I certainly didn't expect bowling balls to have asymmetric cores,
我当然没有料到保龄球会有不对称的核心
but it turns out what looked like perfect spheres,
但是看起来像是完美球体的保龄球
actually have three different principal axes of rotation.
其实有三个不同的转动主轴
Minimum moment of inertia,
最小惯量轴
maximum moment of inertia
最大惯量轴
and intermediate moment of inertia.
以及中间轴
- So this right here is our Dark Code.
我们这球叫“暗黑代码”
This is one of our asymmetric ball that has the Rad 4 core in it.
这是个非对称核心的球  里面放了“Rad 4”
So this has a preferred spin axis.
所以它有一个偏好的转轴
And what we're going to do now
我们现在要把球放在仪器上观察球的转动
is we're going to put it onto the determinator
and show how it actually will spin it and find it
无论我们以哪个方向把球放进仪器  它都能让球旋转、并找到转轴
no matter how we position it on there.
- [Derek] So you spin them up on this machine
所以你先让球在机器上转起来
until they settle into the way they like to spin
它们最后会绕着保龄球手所说的偏好转轴（PSA）转动
where the bowlers call their preferred spin axis or PSA.
（即 最大惯量轴）
But why would you want a ball to be an asymmetric top?
但是保龄球手为什么会希望球有一头不对称呢
Well, professional bowlers drill their balls
职业球手会在他们的球上钻孔
so that at lunch the axis of rotation
所以把球掷出时  旋转轴将位于最小惯量轴和最大惯量轴之间
is somewhere between the minimum and maximum moment of inertia.
And as a result, as the ball goes down the lane spinning,
这就导致了  当球沿着球道前进时会高速旋转
it precesses like a gyroscope.
像陀螺仪一样“进动”
进动：最常见于天文学
指自转轴受某些因素影响
相对于空间中的惯性坐标系
所发生的缓慢且连续的变化
The axis of rotation rotates around
旋转轴在起始点周围旋转
causing the point of contact between the ball and the lane to change.
使得球与地面的接触点不断改变
This precession means that different parts of the ball contact the lane.
这种进动意味着  球每自转一圈  接触地面的部分都不同
进动：最常见于天文学
指自转轴受某些因素影响
相对于空间中的惯性坐标系
所发生的缓慢且连续的变化
And you can see this when the ball back by the spread-out lines of oil on the ball surface.
你可以观察到球面上一圈圈的油迹线
Bowlers call this track flare, and it's desirable
球手们称之为“瓜皮线”  这样的轨迹是比较理想的
*没查到track flare这个术语的中文
翻译时只好直接根据
视频中的形态来意译
because it means once the ball hits the unoiled part of the lane,
这种轨迹意味着  球一旦进入到球道后程不涂油的部分
it gets traction faster
它会更快地获得摩擦力
and hooks more dramatically back to the pins.
并且更显著地钩向球瓶的方向
This is what asymmetric cores are used for.
这就是非对称核心的功能
They have larger differences between their moments of inertia in different axes
其不同主轴上的转动惯量之差（术语“RG差值”）要更大
or what bowlers call RG differential,
which makes the ball precess.
这导致球会产生进动
If you spin a ball around it's minimum or maximum moment of inertia,
如果让球绕着最小/最大惯量轴旋转
it processes less and there's much less flair,
进动的幅度会比较小  瓜皮线也会窄得多
meaning oil builds up on one part of the ball.
这意味着油会在球上的同一个部分积累
This reduces the friction over the dry part of the lane
这会减少球在干燥地面上的摩擦
so the ball hooks less.
所以钩球幅度会变小
- See the oil there, very faintly,
- 看这里的油迹 非常淡
but it's pretty much next to the finger,
但在拇指周围相当多油
right next to the thumb,
and it just continues to be right that way
痕迹沿着这条线延续
all the way around the ball.
绕球一圈
- [Derek] But how important are each of these factors in actually getting the best shot?
但要想完美地一球全倒  这些因素到底有多少影响？
Well, the US Bowling Congress, or USBC,
美国保龄球协会（USBC）
the governing body that sets all rules and regulations for US bowling.
也就是设计了美国保龄球一切规则规章的管辖实体
They did a landmark study in 2008,
他们在2008年进行了一次重要的实验
trying to tease out the most significant factors that affect ball motion.
试图找出对保龄球的运动影响最大的因素
In order to determine the impact of each factor,
为了确定每个因素分别有多大影响
they had to make sure that throws were identical.
他们需要确保每次投出的球都完全一致
So they turned to Harry,
所以他们选择了“哈里”
at the time, the most consistent bowler in the world.
当时他是世界上最稳定的保龄球手
He is a robot.
“他”是个机器人
Bowling robots are designed to be able to throw hundreds of identical shots.
保龄球机器人可以投出上千个完全一样的球
In fact, the robot Earl, Harry's successor in 2011,
实际上，哈里的传人——机器人“伯爵”
actually lost to Chris Barnes when he debuted
在它的出道战中输给了克里斯·巴恩斯
in part because his throws were so consistent.
部分原因是“伯爵”投的球太稳定了
He wore away the oil in a single part of the lane.
它的球蹭掉了同一个路径上的油
So his shots hooked too much.
所以它的球拐弯的幅度太大
The people managing him did their best to adjust to the oil conditions,
尽管“伯爵”的维护者尽了最大的努力来适应油的影响
but few people are Chris Barnes.
但他们毕竟比不了克里斯·巴恩斯
The USBC ball motion study
USBC的保龄球运动研究  使用了哈里来扔出数千个不同的球
used Harry to throw thousands of shots with different bowling balls.
And they found that the center of gravity affected the ball motion relatively little.
他们发现  球的重心几乎不影响球的运动
Around the same level as environmental factors like room temperature or humidity.
球的重心造成的影响力跟温度、湿度等环境因素半斤八两
RG, and RG differential,
RG 和 RG 差值
essentially the moment of inertia
也就是转动惯量
and difference between maximum and minimum moments of inertia.
以及最大惯量与最小惯量的差值
That affected the ball motion significantly more.
转动惯量对球的运动的影响力明显更大
But the factor that affected ball motion the most was the surface of the ball.
但影响力最大的因素  是球的表面
The top five individual factors were
影响最大的五个因素分别是
the amplitude of surface roughness,
球面的粗糙度
meaning the height of microscopic spikes on the ball;
也就是球面上微小的突起
the coefficient of friction with an oiled lane;
球与球道打油部分之间的摩擦系数
the surface roughness by spacing,
球面粗糙处的空间分布
that is the distance between microscopic spikes;
即微小突起之间的距离
the coefficient of friction with the dry lane;
球与球道未打油部分之间的摩擦系数
and how quickly the ball surface absorbs oil.
还有球吸收润滑油的速度
Now, bowlers recognize just how important the surface of their ball is.
保龄球手明白  自己的球的表面有多重要
They pay close attention to what it's made of and how it's finished.
他们很重视球面的材料与抛光
Rougher finishes, give the ball more traction in the oil
抛光时做粗糙  能让球在有油的部分获得更大牵引
and get it to start hooking earlier.
让保龄球能更快转向
This is useful for long oil patterns and slower axis rotation.
这最适合打油部分较长的球道、自转较慢的球
- Sometimes maybe I'll go to a little more sanded ball or a little more ball surface
我有时会选择稍微粗糙一点的球
to get it into a roll quicker for me,
来让球转得更快
because they use a lot of oil.
因为能吸收更多润滑油
- These two shots are thrown identically.
这两个球以完全相同的姿态抛出
The only difference is the ball on the left has a rougher surface.
唯一的区别是，左边的球  表面更粗糙
Rough surfaces act like winter tires,
粗糙的表面就像冬季胎一样
helping to dig into the oil and give the ball traction.
让球能更好地吸油、抓地、获得牵引力
They also act as badly as winter tires on a clean road on a totally dry lane.
冬季胎在干净路面上不好用  粗糙的球在没打油的球道上也亦然
They actually have less friction because their rougher exteriors
此时它们的摩擦力反而更少  因为粗糙的表面导致抓地面积更少
mean that less surface area is touching the lane.
You can get many different levels of smoothness
光滑程度有几个不同的等级
up to a near mirror shine.
最光滑的就像镜子一样
This is better for short oil patterns
这适合打油部分较短的球道
to prevent the ball hooking too much, too early.
这可以让球不会太早转向
Ultimately, pro bowlers carry many different balls to each competition.
总的来说  保龄球的职业球手会带很多不同的球去比赛
- I'm not afraid to change balls in the middle of the game.
我不怕打到一半换球
I go to the game and I've got like a spare, a spare, a spare.
比如说哪场比赛时我连续三次都是补中、补中、补中
spare：补中，在一轮比赛中
第一球没有让球瓶全倒
第二球才清掉了其余球瓶
All right. It's time to change balls.
行吧  应该换个球了
- [Derek] Yeah.
没错
- So now I gotta find the right ball to
所以我得找到最适合这个球道的球
get down the lane again and find the proper,
把换了的球丢上球道  找到最适合这条道的
which usually I have a pretty good idea.
很多时候我都知道该选哪个
- [Derek] So they select their ball a little like a golfer selects their club,
所以他们像高尔夫球手挑球杆一样  会根据赛道条件来选球
to suit the conditions.
But does all this tech actually make people better bowlers?
但这些技巧能让人打的更好吗
Well, over the last 20 years,
在过去二十年里，平均分数上升了超过五分
average scores have increased by more than five points.
Plus the number of perfect 300 games bowled per year per thousand bowlers
每年每千人打出完美300分局的数量
has increased dramatically since the 1980s.
从上世纪80年代起  也有了不可思议的增长
This graph shows the percent change year over year.
这个表展示了每年完美局的占比
In 1976,
在1976年
soaker balls, balls chemically softened to absorb oil and hook more, were banned,
海绵球被禁止了  这种球是用化学手段软化的  更加吸油、转向更好
and there was a dip in perfect games.
完美局的比例大幅下跌
But the same year a new rubber ball was introduced,
但同年，一种新型的橡胶球“不伦瑞克 LT-48”发售了
the Brunswick LT-48
and more 300 were hit in the years that followed.
完美局的比例在下一年又增加了
In 1991, reactive resin balls were introduced
在1991年，树脂球发布
and there was another significant jump.
这个比例又一次增长
Now, obviously there were other improvements in equipment and natural variability,
很明显  现在的设备更加完善  环境变量也更加稳定
but some of the big changes do correlate
但最大的影响还来自于新型球的发布
with the introduction of new ball technology.
So yes, the wild bowling ball technologies out there,
所以  每当一种疯狂的保龄球黑科技出现时
especially anything to do with surface,
尤其是跟球面有关的科技
significantly affect ball motion and your bowling game.
都会显著地影响球的运动、影响比赛
But ball motion is likely minutely affected by hundreds of other factors.
不过还有数百个因素对球的运动产生微小的影响
Even the color of the ball can have a small impact.
甚至球的颜色也会产生微小的影响
A USBC study in 2016 found that
USBC在2016年的一次研究发现
different pigments absorb oil at different rates.
不同的涂料吸收润滑油的速度不同
Bowling is the sport of re-invention.
保龄球是再发明的运动
That goes back to ancient Egypt,
其历史能够追溯到古埃及
but has transformed many times.
但已经多次脱胎换骨
Now, when you get up to throw a single shot,
现在，当你要扔出一个球时
you have to think about the oil pattern on the lane,
你要考虑球道上润滑油的厚度
the stage of the game and how the pattern has shifted,
比赛的阶段、润滑油厚度的改变
the weight block in your ball,
保龄球里的配重块
whether you want symmetric or asymmetric,
是对称还是非对称
which axis you'll spin it about to affect precession,
让它以哪个轴旋转  来影响进动
where the center of mass is to pull the ball to the left, to the right,
球的质心会把球往左拉还是往右拉
what the cover stock is made of
球面是什么材质
and whether it's rough or smooth,
是粗糙还是光滑
all to make a shot that skids, hooks, and rolls
只为了能够扔出一球  经过滑行、转弯、滚动
to the pins between boards 17 and 18 and a half
at as close to a six degree angle as you can master.
尽量以6°的入射角  打到17号+半条18号板上的球瓶
Now do that again 12 times in a row
丢出12次完美球
and you have a perfect game.
你就达成了完美局